Finding Aid for Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Records 1911-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Records
1911-2007
1940-1995
Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan.
The records of Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan document the history of the organization and the family planning services it has provided to Michigan residents. The records are a good source of information on the history of birth control, abortion, sex education, and women’s health issues in the state from the 1930s to the turn of the twenty first century. In addition to the Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan files, the collection includes records documenting the Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan and Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan, dating from the period before these two organizations merged with Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. Materials include board minutes and reports, correspondence, organizational handbooks and policy statements, pamphlets, newsletters, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, and videotapes.
85523 Bj 2
9.75 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were deposited in several accessions beginning in 1967 by Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan and its predecessor the Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood (donor 4483 ). In 2010, the organization under its new name, Planned Parenthood of Mid and South Michigan (donor no. 10425 ) deposited additional records.
The record group is open for research.
The Mother's Clinic, Inc., established in Detroit in 1927, was the first contraceptive clinic opened in Michigan. Shortly thereafter, individuals in other Michigan communities started local committees to disseminate information about contraception. A committee was established in Ann Arbor in 1932, followed by the opening of the Ann Arbor Maternal Health Clinic in 1935. Located in a seven-room house at 738 N. Main Street, its facilities included a living room, examining room, interview room, and lavatory. Dr. Inez Wisdom became the clinic director, an eight member board was organized, and by-laws were adopted. A three hundred dollar gift from the Ann Arbor Community Fund financed the first year of operation. The clinic was open one day a week, and serviced referrals from area health and social agencies.
In 1936, many of the clinic's expenses were covered by the Ann Arbor Community Fund; however, these monies did not pay for services for rural clients. In order to provide these services, the clinic collected donations. In addition to raising funds, a Medical Advisory Board for the Ann Arbor Maternal Health Clinic was also established in 1936.
Heavy use of the clinic's services demonstrated the community's need for organizations devoted to issues of birth control. In 1940, the Maternal Health League of Ann Arbor was incorporated. (The Ann Arbor Maternal Health Clinic was included in the League.) Two years later, the name "Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood, Ann Arbor Chapter" was adopted to comply with changes made by Planned Parenthood at the national and state levels. The remaining years of the 1940s saw developments in publicizing the organization's offerings. A radio series was started as well as the posting of weekly items in the Ann Arbor News. A speaker's bureau and volunteer training program were also established. In 1948, the name of the organization was changed once again to "Michigan League for Planned Parenthood, Washtenaw County".
The 1950s witnessed continued expansion of the programs offered by the Michigan League for Planned Parenthood, Washtenaw County. These included marriage counseling, referral services for infertility cases, and tests for cancer. In 1954, the Michigan League for Planned Parenthood dissolved, leaving the organization affiliated with the National League only; the clinic's name changed to the Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood. In spite of these changes, clinic facilities were improved and the office enlarged. The clinic's patient load increased and clinic hours were extended to accommodate this. Another clinic was established in Ypsilanti.
Increased growth and community acceptance characterized the 1960s at the Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood. The patient load increased from 695 in 1961 to 2,182 in 1968. A study of the Enovide pill was established in 1961 and continued in the following year. In 1964, the clinic's hours of operation were increased and new staff members were hired. During this year, six research projects were in process including a study of the intra-uterine device. The following year, the organization submitted a proposal to the Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) to implement family planning projects using outreach workers. Legislative measures allowing public health and welfare workers to initiate discussion of birth control methods with clients were also passed in 1965. These would greatly shape the clinic's future programs and services. Additionally, the family planning proposal submitted in 1965 to the OEO was approved in 1966.
New programs were also established in the 1970s. The Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood established a youth program in 1972 named "Express Clinic." Express offered youth counseling on sex related topics as well as confidential pregnancy testing, medical services, and referrals. The Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood became the first Planned Parenthood affiliate to offer vasectomy services when it opened the Vasectomy Clinic in June of 1973. The addition of first-trimester abortion services in December of the same year brought changes to the clinic's structure. The number of volunteers working at the clinic was reduced by one-half at this time because of the need for professional staff to service clients seeking abortion services.
The 1980s also witnessed increased programming and major changes to the organization. Recognizing that teenagers receive much of their information about sex through their peers, the Peer Education Program was established in 1981. The goal of this program was to combat misinformation about sex. In 1983, the name of the Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood changed to Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan (PPMM). The following year, Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan moved to a new building. Although the organization had moved several times since its establishment, this new home was the first that was designed especially for the organization. In 1984, the number of patients served annually numbered 5,203, and educational services were delivered to 8,369 individuals. Groups opposing freedom of choice grew strong in the mid 1980s. As opposition to abortion increased, Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan offered opportunities for the community to explore and discuss this issue. The organization held a forum on the movie "Silent Scream" in 1985. Other activities included discussions focusing on the issues of reproductive freedom and projects to influence legislative protection of reproductive rights. In 1987, Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan experienced its first anti-abortion picket.
The turn of the century saw a period of consolidation among regional chapters of Planned Parenthood. In 1969 the Twin Cities Area Planned Parenthood Association was formed to serve Berrien County, Michigan. As its area of service expanded, its name was changed to Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan. This organization had clinics in Niles, South Haven, and Benton Harbor, and worked in cooperation with Country Family Planning clinics throughout Berrien, Cass, and Van Buren Counties. In 1998, Planned Parenthood of Southwestern Michigan merged with Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan to form Planned Parenthood Mid-Michigan Alliance. In 2007, this organization merged with Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan, which had served the metropolitan Detroit area since 1922. The newly formed organization was called Planned Parenthood of Mid and South Michigan.
The Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan record group covers the period of time from the founding of the organization in 1935 through 2007. The history of the organization is documented in this collection. Extensive information about the services offered by Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan can also be found in this collection. These include medical, counseling, and educational activities.
Subjects:
Abortion.; Birth control.; Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan.; Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan.; Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood.; Pro-choice movement--Michigan.; Reproductive health.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Birth control.; Counseling.; Demonstrations--Michigan.; Pro-choice movement--Michigan.; Pro-life movement--Michigan.; Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan.; Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan.; Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Michigan.; Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood.
Contributors:
Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Negatives (photographs); Slides (photographs); Videotapes.
- History/Organizational Documents, 1939-1987
  The History/Organizational Documents series contains information about the founding of the Ann Arbor Maternal Health Clinic, later renamed the Washtenaw League for Planned Parenthood and finally Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. The documents collected in this series span the years from 1939 through 1987. They offer a detailed history of the organization from its founding through the 1960s. They also record changes in the organization's services and affiliations. The folder entitled "Historical Sketches, 1949-1987" contains particularly rich historical information.
  - Ann Arbor Maternal Health Clinic Certificates, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Applications for National Affiliation, 1952-1964 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1939-1984 (Box 1)
  - "Birth Control in Ann Arbor, Michigan: A View of the 1930s", 1980 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws, 1943-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Relating to Early History of Organization, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
  - Early History, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Founder's Room Dedication and Reminiscences, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Historical Sketches, 1949-1987 (Box 1)
  - History of Mid-Michigan and Washtenaw County Affiliates, undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Senate Resolution No. 49 (Commemorating 50th anniversary of Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan), 1985 (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Historical Materials, 1951-1964 (Box 1)
  - "Planned Parenthood Beginnings", 1959 (Box 1)
- Policy Statements/Manuals, 1948-1989
  The Policy Statement/Manuals series includes documents which record information about the policies of Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. It includes handbooks for staff and volunteers as well as policy statements. Some of the policies and manuals pertain to the National League of Planned Parenthood, but most are concerned only with the Mid-Michigan affiliate. Other materials pertain to a specific program offered by PPMM. Not only do they record information about the services offered by Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan, but they also illustrate the organization's views of its services. The years covered in this series range from 1948 through 1989.
  - Job Descriptions, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Orientation Manuals, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Policies and Practices, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America Affiliate Handbook, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America Policy Statements, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America Issues Manual, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Handbook, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Sexual Education Handbook, undated (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Volunteer Handbook, undated (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood World Population Handbook, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Staff and Patient Outlines, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood League of Washtenaw County Policy Statements, 1948; 1969-1974 (Box 1)
- Administrative Files, 1942-2004
  The Administrative Series contains records created between 1942 and 2004. This series documents the administrative workings of Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. It has been further subdivided into six subseries. The first subseries, Annual Meeting Minutes, contains minutes from annual meetings held between 1952 and 1988. Although not every year is represented, the minutes offer an overview of the organization's activities. The Board of Directors subseries includes handbooks for individuals on the board as well as meeting minutes spanning the years 1948 through 1977. Minutes of meetings as well as the reports included in the Executive Committee subseries offer another source of information about the major issues facing Planned Parenthood. The Correspondence and Memoranda subseries includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence. The Reports and Lists subseries includes annual reports, budget information, and reports about the number and kinds of services the clinic offered. These documents offer the researcher insight into the achievements and challenges facing PPMM. They also illuminate PPMM's impact and role in the community. It should be noted that these are high level organizational reports and lists. Reports of specific committees may be found in the Committees and Departments subseries. As its title suggests, this subseries offers an overview of the committees and departments comprising PPMM. The names of the committees and departments offer information about what PPMM saw as the challenges facing them. Documents in this subseries also present detailed information about the nuts and bolts of these bodies.
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1952-1988; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Board of Directors Handbook, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Planned Parenthood League of Washtenaw County Board of Directors Handbook, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1948-1977; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1948-1977; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1960-1976; 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Management Meetings, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1973-1977; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda
    - Board of Directors-outgoing, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Congressional Representatives, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
    - Executive Officers-outgoing, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1978; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports and Lists
    - Annual Reports, 1942-2004; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Clinical Reports
      - Annual Totals, Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti, 1958-1971 (Box 2)
      - Monthly Patient Data, Ann Arbor, 1961-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Monthly Patient Data, Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - Monthly Patient Data, Lansing, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Monthly Patient Data, Ypsilanti, 1961-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Financial Statements and Budget Statistics, 1958-1977 (Box 3)
    - List of Committees, Staff, Executive Board, and Volunteers, 1959-1976 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Reports, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - President's Reports, 1949; 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Statistics, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Teen Family Planning Reports, 1978-1987 (Box 3)
  - Committees and Departments
    - Ad Hoc Committee for Statewide Affiliation, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Affiliate Medical Committee, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Community Education Committee, 1970-1977 (Box 3)
    - Education Committee
      - Annual Reports, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1965-1971; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1966-1977 (Box 3)
      - Rosters, 1967-1972 (Box 3)
    - Education Department Annual Report, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Male Education Committee, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Medical Advisory Committee
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1962-1977; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Committees, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Nominating Committee
      - Annual Report, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    - Personnel Committee
      - Duties and Minutes, 1964-1978 (Box 3)
      - Policies, Job Descriptions, and Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Structure Committee By-Laws, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Planning Committee for Family Planning for Medical Services, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Program Review Committee, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Public Affairs Committee
      - Memoranda and Information Sheets, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
      - Materials and Guidelines, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Speaker's Bureau
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Evaluations, 1970-1973; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
    - Structure and Study Committee Minutes, 1968 (Box 3)
- Working Files, 1964-1995
  The Working Files series consists of documents created and collected by PPMM to inform work on specific topics. These documents span the time period between 1964 and 1995. Several subseries are of particular note. The Abortion subseries documents the rise of opposition to abortion and responses to this opposition by abortion rights activists and organizations. Two subseries pertaining to programs developed by PPMM are especially valuable. The first is the Express Teen Clinic subseries that documents this PPMM program and local reactions to it. The subseries entitled Peer Education Program describes the second initiative. Founded on the belief that teenagers get most of their information about sexuality from their peers, the Peer Education Program was developed. By educating a small group of teenagers who would in turn educate other teenagers, misinformation about sexuality could be combated. The Youth Oriented Material subseries offers further information pertaining to programs directed at teenagers. Insight into the issues surrounding family planning can be found in the subseries with this name. It includes information on family planning resources, projects, and services. The Legislative subseries documents legislative initiatives on abortion during this period. Finally, the Statistics subseries offers compiled information pertaining to the various procedures and services offered by the organization.
  - Abortion
    - Abortion Rights Coalition, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Anti-Abortion Material, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Clinic Questionnaire, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Clinic Statistics, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Clinic Studies, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Washtenaw County Medical Society, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Fake Clinics, 1985-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Medicaid, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Council for the Study of Abortion, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Data, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
    - Papers and Addresses Relating to Michigan, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
    - Pro-Abortion Reports, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
    - Reference Material, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Annotated Guide to Published Information, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - Art Exhibits, 1985-1987 (Box 4)
  - "Ask Planned Parenthood" Newspaper Column, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Clinic Violence, 1986-1992; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Express Teen Clinic
    - Handouts, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Outlines, Procedures, Duties, Responsibilities, undated (Box 4)
    - Publicity and Local Media, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Results of Study, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Statistics, 1974-1977 (Box 4)
    - Student Papers, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Family Planning
    - Advisory Committee on Family Planning Project, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Family Planning Advisory Council Meeting, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Family Planning and Public Information Workshop, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Family Planning Hospitals Conference Proceedings, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Family Planning Needs and Resources in Southeast Michigan, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Family Planning Reports, 1966-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Governor's Conference on Strengthening the Family, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Inputs for Michigan's Plan for Public Family Planning Services, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Family Planning Workshops Proposals, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1974 (Box 4)
    - Publicly Funded Family Planning Programs, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Preliminary Report of the Committee on Social Services, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Resources for Family Planning in Michigan, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Services Provided to Families and Dependent Children, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Goals, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Gonorrhea Test
    - Female Test Results, 1972-1977; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Information Sheets, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
    - Information Statistics, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Health Care Reform, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Legislation
    - Abortion Law Reform, Proposal B, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
    - Clinic Protection, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Freedom of Choice Act, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
    - H.B. 4049, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Regulation of Gender-Based Abortions, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Title X, 1981-1995; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Title X Action Plan, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Title X/Gag Rule, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Library User's Guide (Box 5)
  - Marketing Plan, 1982-1988 (Box 5)
  - News Releases, 1967-1977 (Box 5)
  - News Summaries, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Publicity/Mailings, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Office of Economic Opportunity
    - Budget and Finance Statistics, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Project Report, 1967-1969; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Project Study Committee, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Staff Positions, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Operational Plans, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Parental Consent Brochures, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Parental Consent/Rebecca Bell, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Peer Education Program
    - Course Syllabus and Materials, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
    - Evaluation by Rocco de Pietro, Ph.D., 1984 (Box 5)
    - Evaluations, 1985 (Box 5)
    - History, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Parent Questionnaires, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Reports, 1982-1987 (Box 5)
    - Towsley Proposal, 1981-1985 (Box 5)
  - Press Releases, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Reproductive Rights Votes, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Statistics and Information
    - Fact Sheets: Abortion, 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - Information Sheets, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
    - Fact Sheets: Birth Rates, Population, Abortion, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
    - Fact Sheets: Births, Venereal Disease, Family Planning, 1977-1979 (Box 5)
    - Information Guide, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Information Sheets: Birth Control Devices, 1975 (Box 5)
    - General Information, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Women's Vote Project, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
  - Youth-Oriented Material
    - Adolescent Sexuality/Teenage Pregnancy Bibliography, 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Birth Control Education in Schools" Legislation, 1968-1975; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Child Care and Mental Health Resources, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
    - Citizen's Committee on Family Life and Sex Education, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Commission on Children and Youth, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Youth in Michigan, 1974-1977; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Sex Education in Local Schools, 1965-1970 (Box 5)
    - Teenage Pregnancy Data (Box 5)
- Clippings and Scrapbooks, 1959-2007
  The Clippings and Scrapbooks series includes newspaper clippings and scrapbooks. The clippings contained in this series illustrate how the local press portrayed PPMM as well as information about the clinic's programs and initiatives. Materials in this series span the years between 1959 and 2007.
  - Abortion, 1970; 2000-2007; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Local Publicity, 1959-2007; 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Michigan Abortion Reform Legislation, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1972-2007; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1960-1963 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1964-1971 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 3: Peer Educators, 1994 (Box 6)
- Publications, 1965-2006